## Erica S. Nielsen

esnielsen@sun.ac.za | +27-(0)78-232-8481

Address: Stellenbosch University Private bag X1, Matieland, 7602,

South Africa

**Website:** esnielsen.github.io **Twitter:** @erica\_at\_work

# **Personal Summary**

My research aims to use novel molecular tools and modelling approaches to describe the adaptive potential of marine species with regards to global change. Additionally, my work is grounded in evidence-based decision-making, and focusses on how molecular metrics can best be integrated into conservation planning practices. My proficiency in project and time management has led to five peer-reviewed publications, with 39 total citations, and the Conservation Rising Star award for my first article. In addition to written communications, I thoroughly enjoy orating my work, and have presented at multiple local and international conferences, one of which I won best presentation for. A few additional strengths include the ability to think broadly and work creatively, taking initiative on projects, and building and maintaining strong interpersonal connections.

#### **Education**

**PhD in Zoology** | Jan 2018 to March 2020 – 'Using multi-species seascape genomics to conserve areas of evolutionary importance', Stellenbosch University

**MSc in Zoology** | Jan 2015 to March 2017 – 'Integrating genetics into marine conservation planning in South Africa', Stellenbosch University, *Cum Laude* 

BSc in Biology | Sept 2010 to March 2014 - University of California Santa Cruz, Cum Laude

### **Awards & Grants**

2019 | Best oral presentation – 12<sup>th</sup> Annual Science Postgraduate Symposium, South Africa

2018 | Conservation Biology Rising Star Award

2018-2020 | NRF Grantholder Scholarship (R 90,000)

2016-2017 | NRF Freestanding Masters Scholarship (R 80,000)

## **Employment**

Biology Tutor | Stellenbosch University | July 2015 – May 2019

- Designed tutoring exercises and practicals for first and third year biology students
- Tutored a class of roughly 25 students on introductory biology subjects

Lab Technician | Okinawa Institute of Science and Technology | July 2017 - Oct 2017

- Assisted with sampling and culturing of the tunicate, Oikopleura dioica
- Aided transcriptomic sequencing lab work and data analyses

## **Technical Skillset**

Bioinformatics | R programming | Molecular lab work | Marxan & Zonation | ArcGIS & QGIS | ABC analyses

#### **Peer Reviews**

**Conservation Biology** 

#### Peer Reviewed Publications

- Henriques R., Mann B.Q., **Nielsen E.S.**, Hui C., von der Heyden S. Extending biodiversity conservation with functional and evolutionary diversity: a case study of South African Sparid fishes. 2020. African Journal of Marine Science.
- **Nielsen, E.S.**, Henriques, R., Toonen, R.J., Knapp, I., Guo, B., von der Heyden, S. 2018. Complex signatures of genomic variation of two non-model marine species in a homogeneous environment. BMC Genomics.19: 347.
- **Nielsen, E.S.**, Henriques, R., Beger, M., Selkoe, K., von der Heyden, S. 2017. Multi-species genetic objectives in spatial conservation planning. Conservation Biology. 31: 872-882.
- Henriques, R., **Nielsen, E.S.**, Durholtz, D., Japp, D. and von der Heyden, S. 2017. Genetic population sub-structuring of kingklip (*Genypterus capensis*—Ophidiidiae), a commercially exploited demersal fish off South Africa. Fisheries Research, 187: 86-95.
- Paranjpe, D.A., Medina, D., **Nielsen, E**., Cooper, R.D., Paranjpe, S.A. and Sinervo, B. 2014. Does thermal ecology influence dynamics of side-blotched lizards and their micro-parasites? Integrative and Comparative Biology, 54: 108-117.

# Publications in Prep or Review (manuscripts upon request)

- **Nielsen, E.S.**, Beger, M., Henriques, R., von der Heyden S. A comparison of genetic and genomic approaches to represent adaptive potential in conservation planning. (in review, Biological Conservation)
- **Nielsen, E.S.**, Henriques, R., Beger, M., von der Heyden S. Multi-model seascape genomics identifies distinct environmental drivers of selection among sympatric marine species. (in review, BMC Evolutionary Biology)
- **Nielsen, E.S.**, Beger, M., Henriques, R., von der Heyden S. Comparing drivers of extant molecular diversity: testing central-margin and refugial-persistence hypotheses in the marine environment. (in prep, Ecography)
- Phair, N. L., **Nielsen, E.S.**, von der Heyden S. Applying genomic data to seagrass conservation. (in prep, Conservation Biology)

# **Teaching Experience**

- **2020** | Co-supervisor for Honours project titled: 'Community distribution modelling as a surrogate for genetic diversity hotspots', Stellenbosch University
- **2020** | Lecturer and teaching assistant for Honours 'Science Communication' short course, Stellenbosch University
- 2020 | Teaching assistant for 'Ecology Field Course', Stellenbosch University
- 2019 | Guest lecturer for Honours 'Statistics in R' course, Stellenbosch University
- **2015-2017** | Teaching assistant for 'Cell Biology', 'Functional Biology', and 'Evolutionary Patterns & Processes' courses, Stellenbosch University

### **Oral Presentations**

- **2020** | 'Spatial planning for the future: using molecular & modeling tools to identify conservation hotspots', *International Marine Conservation Congress*, Online
- **2019** | 'Back to the future: Using climatic stability to predict resilience hotspots for conservation', *Conservation Symposium*, South Africa & *Science Postgraduate Symposium*, South Africa
- **2019** | 'Inferring evolutionary significant areas from climatic stability and genetic diversity', Western Indian Ocean Marine Science Association Symposium, Mauritius
- **2018** | 'Conserving adaptive potential: a multispecies comparison across molecular markers', *Conservation Symposium*, South Africa